All
right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, apologies for the slight delay here. Yes,
make some of tomorrow's here. Okay,
we are
in
מסכת מכות Masechet Makkot in the third chapter on the top of
עמוד... Amud... דף טז. Daf Tet Zayin. And this is like the
welcome to גמרא Gemara roller coaster kind of thing. Okay, we're in
the מחלוקת Machloket between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish
Lakish.
The discussion is לאו הניתק לעשה. Lav Hanitak Le'aseh. The examples of
לאו הניתק לעשה Lav Hanitak Le'aseh as we'll see in just a
minute are a few cases in the תורה Torah where the תורה
Torah says do not do something, but if you do it, then
do that. Okay? And I think you started some examples yesterday and
more are to come this morning. For example, one of the classics
is the שילוח הקן, Shiluach Ha-ken, right? Don't do it, we'll read
it later. Send,
don't take the babies on the mother, send the mother, which is
coming first, but this is basically a combination of a negative with
a positive commandment. Okay, so far so good. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish have a disagreement, have a מחלוקת, Machloket,
when does מלקות, Malkot, when do lashes kick in? Okay?
Is it at the point where I don't do the no and
have not yet done the yes? That would be ריש לקיש. Reish
Lakish. Or is it at a point where I don't do the
no and I cancel the possibility to do the yes? Everybody
is doing this,
but I've listened to it like... Yeah, I know.
You started yesterday and now we're going to do the rest and
continue. Yes? We're good with it?
Okay.
The
important thing is that normally
negative
commandments will result in lashes. Negative commandments that are attached to a
positive commandment will not result in lashes because I have the potential
of doing the positive.
לאו שאין בו מעשה, Lav she-ein bo ma'aseh, אין לוקין.
ein lokin. לאו שאין בו
מעשה, אין לוקין
עליו lav she-ein bo
ma'aseh ein lokin
alav. in general. לאו שיש בו מעשה, Lav she-yesh bo ma'aseh, כן
לוקין.
ken lokin.
But now we have a different kind of a לאו, Lav, and
this is why I said the welcome to גמרא Gemara roller coaster.
We have a לאו Lav that is attached to an עשה. Aseh.
Example, which we are coming at the top of 16.
This is what we, I believe
you left off yesterday.
Fifth line
towards from the end. The classic example is ולא תותירו ממנו
עד בוקר
Velo Totiru Mimenu
Ad Boker והנותר ממנו עד בוקר באש תשרופו. Vehanotar Mimenu Ad Boker
Ba-esh Tisropu. So do not leave from the sacrifice till the morning,
right? This is in שמות יב Shemot Yud Bet about the פסח
Pesach sacrifice. Don't leave from it till the morning, but if you
leave, then burn it in fire. Okay? בא הכתוב ליתן עשה אחר
לא תעשה לומר שאין לוקין עליו דברי רבי יהודה. Bah hakatuv liten
Aseh achar lo ta'aseh lomar she-ein lokin alav divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So
here we have an עשה, Aseh, a positive commandment, that comes after
a negative commandment. I.e., ולא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר והנותר ממנו עד
בוקר באש ישרף, Velo Totiru Mimenu Ad Boker Vehanotar Mimenu Ad Boker
Ba-esh Yisarev, in case you did not complete the ולא תותירו Velo
Totiru then you can burn it later. Okay? This is דברי רבי
יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. And as we'll see, before you attack it,
as
we'll see, maybe remember from yesterday, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish learn slightly
different things from the same רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and we'll come
to a point where we have a conflict in two things that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying. Okay? So
I'm going to refer to some of my notes because I was
definitely on the roller coaster and if you want to
help.
Another piece that is important in this מחלוקת machloket is what I
put on the board here. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan think that התראת
ספק hatra'at safek is considered an התראה, hatra'ah, אסרה? asrah? And now
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is considered that התראת ספק hatra'at safek is
not really an התראה. hatra'ah. So the question is where in the
space between these two actions has the person fulfilled this לאו? lav?
Has the person fulfilled this construct? Yes?
Okay. So if
the
person fulfills it, then it's over. But when is the point of
this התראה? hatra'ah? When somebody is not leaving something until the morning,
right? I can say to him: 'Oh, if you leave it, then
you're going to transgress the לאו הניתק לעשה.' lav hanitak l'aseh. But
I have time, right? He has until the morning to be to
complete this construct. So where is the point that I can be
מתרה, matreh, מתרא? matra? Huh? מתרא. matra. I will be מתרא. matra.
No, I will be מתרא. matra. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says: 'You
have time until this whole thing is over, until the עשה aseh
can absolutely not be fulfilled,
that is when you did this, when you transgressed it.' But ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish says: 'No, as soon as you did the לאו
lav and you didn't do the עשה, aseh, that's when you can
get מלקות.' malkot. I think that's what I understand.
So what would be
that point where they differ?
To be here because
I will say if you don't
eat...
What I'm saying is what's the difference between their opinions in terms
of: you have until the morning, right, to eat it, so you
haven't transgressed it until the morning, right?
You could eat all night. Let's see if this is more helpful.
We have an example at the bottom of 15. שלוח הקן.
shiluach haken. Oh, there. You can't eat it.
Oh, you mean you've prevented the fulfillment.
Right, right, right, right. And these are the examples that we'll see.
Maybe instead of going there, the example, the classic example which will
withstand the test that we're going to put this construct through is
the mother bird. Right? We say you have to send away the
mother bird. Right? You could take the...
don't take the babies on the mother bird. Okay, so don't take
the babies. שלח תשלח את האם. shaleyach tishalach et ha'em. You have
to send the mother. What if you killed the mother bird? Then
you made sure that you cannot do this עשה. aseh. But as
long as you have the mother bird and you just haven't sent
her, you still have a chance to complete this לאו הניתק לעשה.
lav hanitak l'aseh.
Okay.
This is
Schrödinger's גמרא. Gemara. Right? It's both alive and not alive at the
same time. Okay. It's important that we don't have
מלקות, malkot, we don't have lashes for a לאו הניתק לעשה lav
hanitak l'aseh normally, but we have to see at what point they're
still together and at what point they're apart.
Okay. Let's read a little more. Now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
trying to be more precise with what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
saying. רבי יוחנן דייק הכי: Rabbi Yochanan dayek hachi: טעמא דבא כתוב,
הא לא בא כתוב לוקה. ta'ama de'va katuv, ha lo ba katuv
lokei. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that the text
said באש תשרפו. ba'esh tisrofu. The text gave us this addition, right?
The Torah gave us this addition of: you will burn it in
the fire. If the text didn't say it and then therefore we
didn't do it, that's when you get the lashes. But you have
time to fulfill it. And any time I will say to you:
'Oh, if you don't do it, then whatever, you will transgress,' this
would be an התראת ספק hatra'at safek because I'm not really seeing
you not do the thing you're not doing. Okay? So it's an
התראת ספק. hatra'at safek. For ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, התראת ספק hatra'at
safek is still an התראה. hatra'ah. Is not an התראה. hatra'ah. Okay,
this will change the punishment. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish reads it...
רגע, rega, sorry. אלמא התראת ספק שמה התראה alma hatra'at safek shema
hatra'ah for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. וריש לקיש דייק הכי: v'Resh Lakish
dayek hachi: טעמא דבא כתוב, הא לא בא כתוב לוקה. ta'ama de'va
katuv, ha lo ba katuv lokei. So he understands... see both of
them end up with the מלקות malkot but they come to it
from two different sides. For ריש לקיש... Resh Lakish... על לאו שאין
בו מעשה לוקין עליו al lav she-ein bo ma'aseh lokin alav as
we said in the beginning. If it was just a לאו lav
that has someone just said before already that אין בו מעשה לוקין
עליו. ein bo ma'aseh lokin alav. Okay. ורבי שמעון בן לקיש נמי
Ve-Rabbi Shimon Ben
Lakish nami also הויא דהתראת ספק hava de-hatrat safeik is another proof
from התראת ספק. hatrat safeik. Who סבר לה savar lah as דאידך
תנא de-idach tanna דחזקיה? de-Chizkiyah? No, de-Rabbi Yehuda.
Now Rabbi Yehuda is going to the both of them learn what
they're learning from Rabbi Yehuda and Reish Lakish is learning the issue
of התראת ספק hatrat safeik from another teaching of Rabbi Yehuda. We're
going to sidetrack to a case that is not
under this category it's just to look about התראות ספק hatra'ot safeik
about
doubtful warning okay forewarning. All right. דתניא De-tanya a case הכה זה
וחזר והכה זה קילל זה וחזר וקילל זה הכה שניהם בבת אחת
או קילל שניהם בבת אחת חייב.
Hika zeh ve-chazar ve-hika zeh kilel zeh ve-chazar ve-kilel zeh hika
shneihem be-vat achat o kilel shneihem be-vat achat chayav. רגע Rega
what is the case? The case here is somebody that
the commandment refers to מכה אביו ואמו. makeh aviv ve-imo.
Somebody who beats up his father sorry and is
going to be חייב chayav but there is a doubt in this
הכאה. haka'ah. So what is the case?
A woman was married to I don't know Reuven okay? They got
a divorce. Our
the Torah tells us that there should be at least three months
between the divorce and the remarriage right so that if she's pregnant
we know whose child it is. In this case she got married
almost straight away or let's say after two months she got pregnant
and after seven months she had a child. Okay.
When the child is born we don't know whose child this is.
It could be Reuven's child from a pregnancy of nine months it
could be whatever Levi's child from a pregnancy of seven months. Okay.
This child now goes and beats up Reuven and they
and he was forewarned right he got an התראה hatra'ah that if
he continued if he does that he's going to be liable for
the death penalty didn't pay attention went back and hit the other
father okay
hit Levi. Or he cursed one and then went back and cursed
the other or he hit both of them at the same time
or he cursed both of them at the same time. Now one
of them for sure is the father
and there were beatings or curses so
we
say that he is חייב. chayav. Why is he חייב? chayav? Because
התראת ספק hatrat safeik is considered a התראה. hatra'ah. If he was
warned let's say he was warned with the first guy even though
it was not the father it's like if you hit your father
you will be liable so that is considered התראה hatra'ah acceptable התראה.
hatra'ah.
But we have also the opinion that התראת ספק hatrat safeik is
not a real התראה hatra'ah and here is where Rabbi Yehuda teaches
both for two different occasions. Rabbi Yehuda
אומר בבת אחת חייב omer be-vat achat chayav if this happened
together he is liable but זה אחר זה פטור zeh achar zeh
patur because then that follows the rule that התראת ספק hatrat safeik
is not really a התראה hatra'ah and if it happened at the
time when it didn't happen then he's not going to be liable
and this is what Reish Lakish is learning from. Okay. ורבי יוחנן
נמי Ve-Rabbi Yochanan nami הויא דלאו שאין בו מעשה הוא. hava de-lav
she-ein bo ma'aseh hu. So for Rabbi Yochanan it's not a problem
because he says this is התראת ספק hatrat safeik is a התראה
hatra'ah this is לאו lav that has no מעשה. ma'aseh.
He is beating somebody how's it לאו שאין בו מעשה?
Lav she-ein bo ma'aseh,
That is what it says. Well let's go a little bit and
maybe we'll answer.
If it's a curse maybe it's not a מעשה ma'aseh right but
it's either one.
But רגע
רגע רגע rega rega rega סבר לה savar lah let me go
just a little bit until the חוץ מן המשנה chutz min ha-mishnah
and then we'll see if it will answer it.
He's going back to the חמץ chametz he's not going to the
he's not talking... רגע. rega.
סבר לה כי הא דאמר רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב.
Savar lah ki
ha
de-amar Rav Idi bar Avin amar Rav. סברה לה כי הא דאמר
רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב עמרם אמר רב יצחק אמר רב
יוחנן רב יהודה אומר משום רב יוסי הגלילי
Savra lah ki ha d'amar Rav Idi bar Avin amar Rav Amram
amar Rav Yitzchak amar
Rav Yochanan Rav Yehuda omer mishum Rav Yossi ha-Glili and we'll see
that there's two opinions: כל לא תעשה שבתורה. kol lo ta'aseh she-ba-Torah.
And now we'll break that up. Right? Every negative commandment in the
Torah. לאו שיש בו מעשה לוקין עליו, lav she-yesh bo ma'aseh lokin
alav, לאו שאין בו מעשה אין לוקין עליו. lav she-ein bo ma'aseh
ein lokin alav. So hitting somebody is לאו שיש בו מעשה, lav
she-yesh bo ma'aseh, no? It's not like לא תותירו. lo totiru. Sit
and do nothing and when you do nothing, something happens. It's an
active thing. So therefore לוקין עליו lokin alav and לאו שאין בו
מעשה lav she-ein bo ma'aseh? אין לוקין עליו. ein lokin alav חוץ
מן הנשבע ומימר והמקלל את חבירו בשם.
chutz min ha-nishba
u-meimar ve-ha-mekalel et chaveiro ba-Shem. So there's some exceptions
to this rule. One is somebody who swears falsely and מימר, meimar,
I would translate that... it's תמורה tmura in קרבנות. korbanot. והמקלל
את חבירו בשם, ve-ha-mekalel et chaveiro ba-Shem,
and somebody who curses his fellow
with God's name.
And you can see that some of the things that we haven't
yet raised might come as a surprise. We have a קשיא דרבי
יהודה אדרבי יהודה. kashya d'Rabbi Yehuda a-d'Rabbi Yehuda.
There's two different rules that we learn from Rabbi Yehuda
and
they stand against each other. In the ruling of לא תותירו, lo
totiru, right, ונותר ממנו עד בוקר, ve-notar mimenu ad boker, we don't
have מלקות. malkot. It's a לאו הניתק לעשה lav ha-nitak la-aseh and
there's no מכות. makot. But yes, no מלקות. malkot. But in the
case of the son, I think there are מלקות.
malkot. And ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, okay,
so now we have like whatever who's with who. אי לרבי שמעון
בן לקיש תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי יהודה אי לרבי יוחנן לא קשיא
הא דידיה הא דרביה.
ei l'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish trei tannai aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda
ei l'Rabbi Yochanan lo kashya ha deideh ha d'rabeih.
The case of ריש לקיש Resh Lakish learns that התראת ספק hatra'at
safek is considered a התראה, hatra'ah, right? That's what ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish is saying. And but in the case of מכה אביו, makeh
aviv, התראת ספק hatra'at safek is not considered התראה hatra'ah and we
have
both
these opinions.
And they even go back, let's see. Rabbi Yehuda says לאו שאין
בו מעשה לוקים lav she-ein bo ma'aseh lokim and Rabbi Yossi ha-Glili
לאו שאין בו מעשה לא לוקים. lav she-ein bo ma'aseh lo lokim.
So we seem to have both opinions and Rabbi Yochanan and Rabbi
Shimon ben Lakish, ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, take from both of them.
Okay, let's go back to the לאו הניתק למעשה לעשה lav ha-nitak
le-ma'aseh le-aseh
and see how we can unpack examples that have to do with
this situation. As long as the לאו הניתק לעשה lav ha-nitak la-aseh
is connected to the עשה aseh and not cancelled, then the person
does not get lashes. Let me say this again. As long as
the לאו הניתק לעשה lav ha-nitak la-aseh is connected to the possibility
that the person is going to do the positive commandment associated with
it and not cancelled, then he does not get lashes. This is
Rabbi Yochanan's opinion of קיימו ולא קיימו. kiyamo ve-lo kiyamo. ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish says as soon as you didn't do the עשה, aseh,
we'll see hopefully in examples it'll become a little clearer, but it
is a גמרא Gemara rollercoaster. So ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, קיימו ולא
קיימו, kiyamo ve-lo kiyamo, as soon as he's not doing the עשה
aseh he transgressed and he deserves lashes. For Rabbi Yochanan he has
time. There might be a lot of time as we'll see, but
only when that עשה aseh potential is completely cancelled that's when he
is liable for lashes. Okay,
kind of okay, maybe okay. Alright, so what with the קרבן korban
that has to be burnt? There's no end time yet, is there?
Well, theoretically it says עד הבוקר, ad ha-boker, but yes you have
the whole night, at least you have the whole night. But here
we're going to see situations where it's not a time thing אלא
אלא ela ela but rather you or the person did something in
order to prevent the עשה aseh from happening. Example that's coming up
is שילוח הקן. shiluach ha-ken. If I as long as I hold
the mother bird I can send it at any time and by
that fulfill the מצות עשה. mitzvot aseh. But what if I killed
it?
I by that prevented myself from doing the עשה aseh and I
only did the לאו. lav. I disconnected the לאו lav from the
עשה aseh and now I'm liable. As long as they're connected I
am not going to get lashes.
We're going to have the גמרא Gemara is going to seek examples.
We're going, I'm just going to give you the overview and then
we're going to go into the details because it's so easy to
lose the forest from the— the forest from the trees, the trees
from the forest, or both from each other. Okay, we have שילוח
הקן. Shiluach haken. We have an issue of לא תגזול, lo tigzol,
right? Don't rob somebody, but a poor person, but then you can
be משיב את הגזילה, meishiv et hagezeilah, right? The Torah says both.
You can— don't come to a poor person to take something, but
then you can return it. So those are all— and we have
what you started on yesterday, if somebody rapes a woman, he can't
send her away, right? He has to marry her and take care
of her. So where is that point that this happens? And the
last piece is the פאה. pe'ah. You have to leave the corner
of the field to the stranger, the Levi, and so on. So
it will say לא תכלה פאת שדך לעני ולגר תעזוב. lo techaleh
pe'at sadecha la'ani velager ta'azov. So what if you transgressed the negative
and you did cut the corner of your field? When is the
point that you can't anymore give anything to the poor person and
you can't do the עשה? aseh? Okay.
I am sorry we don't have like a week in order to
unpack this because that's what it felt like to me, but maybe
for everybody else it's easy so then I'm not going to worry
about it. Okay, תנן התם. tanan hatam. הנוטל אם על הבנים. hanotel
em al habanim. Michael, do you have the פסוק? pasuk? Do you
want to read us the פסוק pasuk because the גמרא Gemara doesn't
have it? Yes.
Ah, he gave it to me. Okay. כי יקרא קן ציפור לפניך
בדרך בכל עץ או על הארץ אפרוחים או ביצים והאם רובצת על
האפרוחים או על הביצים לא תקח האם על הבנים. ki yikarei kan
tzippor lefanecha baderech bechol etz o al ha'aretz efrochim o beitzim veha'em
rovetzet al ha'efrochim o al habeitzim lo tikach ha'em al habanim. שלח
תשלח את האם ואת הבנים תקח לך למען ייטב לך והארכת ימים.
shaleach tishalach et ha'em ve'et habanim tikach lach lema'an yitav lach veha'arachta
yamim.
So this is the classic case. If you chance upon a bird's
nest on the way, in the tree or on the ground, there's
fledglings or eggs, and the mother is sitting on the baby birds
or on the eggs, don't take the mother with the eggs or
the baby birds, right? This is the negative. שלח תשלח, shaleach tishalach,
send the mother away, and then the birdies you can take and
you'll even have long life.
Okay.
So now we'll see two ways to understand this and we'll see
our problem. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר לוקה ואינו משלח.
Rabbi Yehuda omer
lokeh ve'eino meshaleach. Rabbi Yehuda holds by the ruling
that you will get מכות makot and not משלח. meshaleach. Why? Because
he thinks, he thinks that the פסוק pasuk is written, is intended
to be backwards. You're first supposed to send the mother bird and
then not take the babies on her. This is how he understands
it. The חכמים Chachamim understand it the other way, so don't attack
him yet on my account because I don't know what to do.
Were both רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish learning
from רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Yeah. So I mean this— if this
is taken on face value this seems more like ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish than רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. That's it, you're done, right? You
don't have time to—
according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the עשה aseh in this case
intends to come before the לאו. lav. Therefore it doesn't cancel it.
Therefore you get
מכות. makot.
See that according to like everything.
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. אוי אוי אוי, oy oy oy, I know,
but not. These are going to be the exceptions. These are going
to be the cases of לאו הניתק לעשה. lav hanitak la'aseh. If
you Google לאו הניתק לעשה, lav hanitak la'aseh, you will find this
גמרא Gemara page. Like this does not appear in other places. This
is, all the situations are here. And we're going to be left
with the mother bird. So let's try. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר לוקה
ואינו משלח.
Rabbi Yehuda omer lokeh
ve'eino meshaleach. וחכמים אומרים משלח ואינו לוקה. vechachamim omrim meshaleach ve'eino lokeh.
See the rabbis go and say by order, right? Don't take, and
if you take, send the mother bird, right? That there is an
עשה aseh attached to the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. זה הכלל כל
מצות לא תעשה שיש בה קום עשה אין חייבים עליה. zeh haklal
kol mitzvat lo ta'aseh sheyesh bah kum aseh ein chayavim aleiah. This
is our rule. This is the חכמים's Chachamim rule. If there is
a מצוה mitzvah that is a negative that is attached to a
positive, there are no מלקות malkot for it as long as you
have a potential of doing the positive. אמר רבי יוחנן אין לנו
אלא זאת ועוד אחרת. amar Rabbi Yochanan ein lanu ela zot ve'od
acheret. This should be the most comforting פסוק, pasuk, most comforting פסוק.
pasuk. statement in this סוגיא. sugya. There's not a lot of cases,
only this and one other.
אמר לו רבי אלעזר, Amar lo Rabbi Elazar, היכא? heicha? אמר לו,
Amar lo, לכי תשכח. lechi tishkach. Rabbi Elazar says where is the
other one? Rabbi Yochanan said go look for it. Fine. נפק דק
ואשכח. Nafak dak ve-ashkach. So this is like an expression. He left
everything he was busy with and he went to look for where
is another case that is a לאו הניתק לעשה lav ha-nitak la-aseh
that we have a possibility of canceling the עשה aseh actively and
it's not like eternal, we can't just keep doing it forever. דתניא,
De-tanya, here, let's see if this example is going to work.
אונס שגירש. Ones she-gerash. Notice the pronunciation, it's אונס ones and not
honest. אונס Ones is active, the person, the rapist that kicks his
wife or no, kicks his raped woman away.
Let me
have to paraphrase this case by stating how disturbing it is but
how I think I want to read it favorably to the תורה
Torah and to the גמרא. Gemara.
The idea possibly like you know you think about it in our
days why would somebody who was raped by another man want to
be married to him. Yes please send her away she doesn't want
to be with you anyway right? But in תורה Torah times I
think it's a mechanism to defend the woman because if she was
raped the chances of her finding a good marriage afterwards is slim
to none. So therefore the תורה Torah says no, לא תוכל לשלחה,
lo tuchal le-shalcha, you cannot send her away all the days of
your life. Like your past action right now has consequences that will
impact you for the rest of your life. Okay, under that, אונס
שגירש, ones she-gerash, אם ישראל הוא, im yisrael hu, מחזיר ואינו לוקה,
machzir ve-eino lokei, ואם כהן הוא, ve-im kohen hu, לוקה ואינו מחזיר.
lokei ve-eino machzir. So what happens? He now divorces the woman that
he raped but the תורה Torah says לא תוכל לשלחה, lo tuchal
le-shalcha, you can never send her away. If he's ישראל, yisrael,
he can bring her back and he doesn't get lashes. He can
still fulfill this עשה. aseh. He can do the positive commandment and
not get lashes. But if he's a כהן, kohen, he can't bring
her back because now he sent her away therefore she's a divorcee,
a כהן kohen cannot marry a divorcee, so he will take the
lashes. Okay. הניחא, Ha-nicha, למאן דתני, le-man de-tani, קיימו ולא קיימו. kiyamo
ve-lo kiyamo.
Okay, this is good for the person, for the ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish people that say you have to fulfill the positive side of
the commandment and if you don't, in the second you didn't fulfill
it then you're liable. אלא למאן דתני, Ela le-man de-tani, ביטלו ולא
ביטלו, bitlo ve-lo bitlo, בשלמא גבי שילוח הקן משכחת לה. Bishlama gabei
shiluach ha-ken mashkachat lah. Wait, okay, you're telling me that the אונס
ones is like שילוח הקן? shiluach ha-ken? In שילוח הקן, shiluach ha-ken,
you have the possibility of killing the mother bird, therefore never having
the option of completing the positive side of the commandment. But here,
what do you mean, why is this the same?
What do you think? Like אלא אונס, ela ones, ביטלו ולא ביטלו,
bitlo ve-lo bitlo, היכי משכחת לה? heichi mashkachat lah? Like how is
this going to work for the person that says you have time?
What are you, are you going to kill... when is this going
to stop? When is this time going to stop? What, you're going
to kill the woman? If you kill the woman then you're going
to be liable for this, right? אי דקטלה, Ei de-katla,
קם ליה בדרבה מיניה, kam leh bi-derabbah mineih, you're going to be
liable for death if you kill the woman. So we need a
different solution for you to not be able to do the positive
aspect of this לאו הניתק לעשה. lav ha-nitak la-aseh. אמר רב שימי
מחוזנא, Amar Rav Shimi me-Chozna, כגון שקיבלה קידושין מאחר. kegon she-kiblah kiddushin
me-acher. Ah, here is an option for you to not be able
to fulfill this
מצוה. mitzvah. Not you חס ושלום, chas ve-shalom, but somebody raped another
woman, took her for a wife, sent her away, the תורה Torah
says do not send her away, you cannot now take her back,
right? You cannot take her back because she accepted קידושין kiddushin from
another person. Wait, wait, that does not make sense. גמרא Gemara is
going to challenge. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, שויתיה שליח, shavitah
shaliach, אי היא קא מבטלה ליה, ei hi ka mavatla leh, אי
לא שויתיה שליח, ei lo shavitah shaliach, כל כמיניה ולא כלום היא.
kol kimeineih ve-lo klum hi. Okay, wait, what do you mean? Like
how did this exactly work now that all of a sudden she
accepted a marriage proposal from somebody
else, right?
Right because he has to
agree because he
can't appoint himself a שליח sheliah on her
behalf without her knowing. Yes and there's a שיטה shita that he
accepted on her behalf.
Yes that's what it said
אקבלה.
akbalah.
Yes
yes Michael was helping me explain this thing. Okay he can't accept
it on her behalf because he has a prior obligation right so
he can't accept her getting married to somebody else. So maybe another
option.
אלא אמר רב שימי מנהרדעא כגון שהדירה ברבים. Ella amar Rav Shimi
mi-Nahardea kegon shedira b'rabim. Ah what if he made a public vow?
I think I touched on this yesterday. They made it על דעת
רבים al daat rabim that you can't get out of.
Okay so here is not yet but we'll get there.
We have to.
I don't want to be a spoiler but wait.
Okay so maybe the way that he can never take her back
is because he did like a נדר ברבים. neder b'rabim. Okay wait
we have two options with this נדר neder business. למאן דאמר נדר
שהודר ברבים אין לו הפרה. L'man d'amar neder shehudar b'rabim ein lo
hafara. Okay some people say נדר neder that was made in public
has no absorption how do you say it right can't get out
of it. אלא למאן דאמר יש לו הפרה מאי איכא למימר דמדירה
על דעת רבים.
Ella l'man d'amar yesh
lo hafara mai ika l'meimar d'madira al daat rabim. Okay so now
we have two different ways to do a נדר. neder. One is
נדר ברבים neder b'rabim he does it in public. One is נדר
על דעת רבים neder al daat rabim with the agreement or with
the understanding of everybody right one is in public he states it
in public one is with the public's opinion agreeing with him or
accepting it.
דאמר אמימר הלכתא נדר שהודר ברבים יש לו הפרה על דעת רבים
אין לו הפרה.
D'amar Ameimar hilchata neder shehudar b'rabim yesh lo hafara al daat
rabim ein lo hafara. So a vow that was made in public
has you can get out of it because you can go back
and do it again in public. But if you did it with
the public's agreement then you can't get out of it. Okay then
like everybody accepts what you're taking.
We're
going to come back to the woman. Because it was ביטול bitul
you can't get out of it. Yes but we're going to come
back at the end of this סוגיא sugya and undo it. Oh
really? Yes. So just stay tuned. Okay. ותו ליכא? V'tu leika? Are
there any more examples to this fun rollercoaster ride of a לאו
הניתק לעשה lav ha-nitak l'aseh besides the mother bird
and the אונס? ones?
והאיכא סימן גזל
משכון ופאה.
Ve-ha-ika siman gezel
mashkon u-feah.
So three more situations that we're going to look at. גזל Gezel
דחמנא אמר. de-rachmana amar. גזל Gezel is whenever stronger than stealing taking
taking something away from somebody. The Torah says לא תגזול lo tigzol
don't do it והשיב את הגזלה ve-heshiv et ha-gezeilah right but then
it says return what you've taken unjustifiably. משכון. Mashkon. Translate משכון. mashkon.
Collateral. Collateral. The Torah says לא תבוא אל ביתו לעבוט עבוטו השב
תשיב לו. lo tavo el beito la'avot avoto hashev tashiv lo. Don't
come to the poor person's home to take the collateral bring it
back to him right so those are more situations where there is
a positive attached to a negative.
השב תשיב לו העבוט כבוא השמש. Hashev tashiv lo ha-avot k'vo ha-shemesh.
ומשכחת לה בקיומו ולוקימו ובטלו ולא בטלו. u-mashkachat lah b'kiyumo v'lokimo u-vitlo
v'lo bitlo. Okay so this works. What about the ביטלו ולא ביטלו?
bitlo v'lo bitlo? The other one. התם כיון דחייב בתשלומין אין לוקה
ומשלם. Hatam keivan de-chayav b'tashlumin ein lokeh u-meshallem. רגע. Rega.
You can pay for what you've taken back and you cannot get
two punishments except for the מוציא שם רע. motzi shem ra. So
either or are you being לוקה lokeh or משלם? meshallem? You can
be משלם. meshallem. So therefore you still have time to fulfill the
עשה aseh maybe not a good example. מתקיף לה רבי זירא האיכא
משכונו של גר ומת הגר.
Matkif lah Rabbi Zeira ha-ika mashkono shel
ger u-met ha-ger. Wait what if it's a collateral of a גר
ger and now the גר ger died? You will not be able
to huh you will not be able to return the you will
not be able to fulfill the עשה aseh because the גר ger
is dead. Right.
He doesn't have any heirs meaning.
Yes yes exactly he doesn't so the loan doesn't go to. to
the next generation. התם גברא בר תשלומי הוא ושיעבודא דגרא הוא דקא
פקע.
Hatam gavra
bar tashlumi hu ve-shibuda de-gera hu de-ka paka. Wait, if the גר
ger dies on you, that's not because you cancelled the עשה. asei.
Maybe you waited too long, but you did not actively do something.
It's not like the mother bird, that you killed the mother bird
and by that prevent yourself from fulfilling this עשה. asei. The גר
ger died, so it's not up to you. It's פקע. paka.
It
was... right, I mean we need a case that you created... impossible.
I mean a case that you made it...
yes, we're looking for a
case that you
made something
impossible, and there's nothing else you can do about it. Right, that's
what we were saying above, I don't know if we fully fleshed
that out, because in the case of the משכון, mashkon, even if
you burnt that משכון, mashkon,
you can still pay for its value, the מצוה mitzvah is there.
Right, whereas if the גר ger dies, it's not on you. You
did not do... right, whereas in the, you know, in the case
before with the woman, you know, you divorced her and you took
the קידושין kiddushin for her, or whatever it is, you've made it
into an עבירה, aveirah, you can't, there's nothing at this... you're done.
I mean, at least at this point. רגע, Rega, you're going to
stay till the end, or you're going to walk out? Hold tight.
But it's also weird in that even with the bird case, that
we say the only time that he's entitled to get lashes is
if he killed the mother bird, as opposed to when the mother
bird died by itself where it's still impossible to send the bird
away. Yeah, but this is because it's a commandment, so it's a
מצוה mitzvah on the person. Don't do this, and if you do
this, do this. If you cannot do the positive because whatever, something
happened, you're, you didn't transgress the whole construct and you're like free.
But if you did something that prevented the עשה asei from happening,
then you're liable, because you actively did something in order to prevent
it. All right, so we had all our great examples, right? The
bird, the אונס, ones, the גזל, gezel, the משכון, mashkon, we settled
all of them, and now we have the פאה, peah, the corner
of the field. והא איכא פאה דרחמנא אמר לא תכלה פאת שדך
וגו' לעני ולגר תעזוב אותם.
Ve-ha ika peah de-rachmana amar lo
techaleh pe'at sadecha etcetera le-ani ve-la-ger ta'azov otam.
Don't cut off the corner of your field, right? Leave it to
the poor and to the convert. דמשכחת לה בקיימו ולא קיימו בטלו
ולא בטלו. De-mashkachat lah be-kiymo ve-lo kiymo bitlo ve-lo bitlo. Okay, so
like
the person that says, as soon as you didn't do the עשה,
asei, you're liable, fine, you cut the corner, you're now liable, but
the other side, how much time do you have to fulfill that
עשה? asei? דתנן מצות פאה להפריש מן הקמה, De-tenan mitzvat peah le-hafrish
min ha-kamah, and the מצוה mitzvah originally is to give away
grain
from the standing sheaves, from the קמה. kamah. לא הפריש מן הקמה
מפריש מן העומרים. Lo hifrish min ha-kamah mafirish min ha-omerim. Okay, so
let's say you cut the whole field and you didn't leave any
standing grain, you can give from the sheaves. לא הפריש מן העומרים
מפריש מן הכרי עד שלא מירח.
Lo hifrish min ha-omerim mafrish min
ha-keri ad she-lo mireach. If it's not from the
עומרים, omerim, you can have the next stage of wheat, עד שלא
מירח, ad she-lo mireach, עד שלא מירח, ad she-lo mireach, until he
did not like make it into a grain, or not grain,
flour,
smoothing it out, what's...
flour. מירח. Mireach.
מירחו מעשר ונותן לו. Mircho ma'aser ve-noten lo.
If he did that, then he has to give the tithing and
give to the לוי. Levi. The לוי Levi gets the tithe because
he has no חלק chelek in ישראל, Yisrael, he has no land,
and so he needs to be given from the field. כי דרבי
ישמעאל דאמר אף מפריש מן העיסה. Ki de-Rabbi Yishmael de-amar af mafrish
min ha-isah. רגע, Rega, so now we're at like, the field is
gone, the sheaves are gone, right? We, and now we have עיסה,
isah, we have porridge kind of thing that's left from this... made
it into dough. Made it into dough. Okay.
I
mean what we're trying to say is that it's, you know, that
you can still, you still always have time, so why, you know,
so where do you get the case of בטלו? bitlo?
But here, but here, what he did actively by making it into
a dough, ודרבי ישמעאל נמי משכחת לה דאכל עיסה. ve-de-Rabbi Yishmael nami
mashkachat lah de-achal isah. So what happened, now we don't have anymore
a פאה, peah, because we made it, we changed the form of
what it is, and we can't anymore give wheat to the poor
person and to the לוי. Levi. We now don't anymore have wheat,
we have
dough,
something else. Can eat it, but it's not...
meaning we found a case it seems because we said חלה Challah
איסור. Issur. Yeah. So then this is חלה Challah or another case
of ביטול. Bitul.
This is a case where we did something actively in order to
cancel the עשה. Aseh. אלא זאת ועוד אחרת. Ella zot ve'od acheret.
So
now we have the two cases of לאו הניתק לעשה Lav hanitak
le'aseh that you actively did something to cancel the עשה Aseh and
by that transgressed. And those cases are the mother bird, if you
חס וחלילה Chas vechalilah killed the mother bird, and the פאה Pe'ah
if you create dough from the פאה Pe'ah changing the form of
what the wheat is and therefore
unable to now fulfill the עשה. Aseh.
Right. So now we have a problem because we've seen that we
have three and we only said it was two.
So that's what we're going to see. אבל עונה לא. Aval onneh
lo. Okay. דאי כאמרינן על דעת רבים אין לו הפרה לדבר הרשות
אבל לדבר מצווה יש לו הפרה.
De'ika amrinan al da'at rabbim ein lo hafarah lidvar hareshut aval lidvar
mitzvah
yesh lo hafarah. Okay,
so in the case of the עונה, Onneh, if he makes a
נדר Neder על דעת רבים, Al da'at rabbim, true, it has no
annulment if it is a דבר רשות, Dvar reshut, if it is
something permissible, but if it is a מצווה Mitzvah as it is
here, he has a הפרה. Hafarah. And here we have a story
that connects to this situation: כי הא דההוא מקרי דרדקי דהוה פשע
בינוקי. Ki ha dehahoo makrei dardekei d'hava pasha beinokei. There was a
teacher who would beat up his students, who was like mean to
his students. אדריה רב אחא. Adrei Rav Acha. Rav Acha sent him
away. He like did a הדיר אותו Hedir oto and said like
this guy's never going to come back. ואהדריה רבינא דלא אשתכח דדייק
כוותיה.
Ve'ahadrei Ravina delo
ishtakach dedayek kavateih.
There was not any teacher who was as good as him. Therefore
it was a דבר מצווה Dvar mitzvah to teach the children. Therefore
you could reinstate him even against the נדר. Neder. And therefore we
learn from it that in case that there is a מצווה, Mitzvah,
you can be מפר את הנדר Mefer et haneder and you can
still fulfill it. And the עונה Onneh therefore even if he takes
a נדר, Neder, he because he has a מצווה Mitzvah לא תשלחנה
Lo tishalchenah and to keep the woman, that נדר Neder can be
annulled and he can fulfill the עשה. Aseh. Good.
Whew.
Okay.
Digging for my cell phone, but I'm good.
If you're good at that, that's huge, David. Kind of good. Okay.
Back to the משנה. Mishnah. We're going to pick up one, at
least one small section and see if we can do this.
If you're anywhere near good then I'm very happy because... Okay.
Back to the משנה. Mishnah. הלוקים, Halokim,
right? We're learning who are הלוקים? Halokim? והאוכל נבלות וטרפות שקצים ורמשים
וכולי. Veha'ochel nevelot utreifot shekatzim uremasim vechulei.
So now we have somebody who's eating dead animals that were not
כשר Kashered properly.
Whatever. All sorts of meats and foods that are not allowed to
be eaten. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. So now let's look
at some specifics. Like some things maybe are obvious, a dead animal
is a dead animal, but let's look at little שרצים, Sheratzim, little
creatures and see some specifics. האי מאן דאכל בינתא. Hai man de'achal
binta. The בינתא Binta is a בינתא דבי כרבא. Binta devei karva.
This is...
Rav Yehuda says this is about somebody who ate this little worm
that lives inside a cabbage.
מלקין
ליה משום שרץ השורץ על הארץ.
Malkin leih mishum
sheretz
hashoraitz
al ha'aretz. Which is interesting.
Here they translated it differently.
Wait a minute, coming up.
This is following תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot under the בינתא Binta if
we have time, because תוספות Tosafot says okay, but like if it's
a simple שרץ Sheretz then what is the גמרא Gemara adding to
me? Like I knew this already, right? This is פשט. Pshat. And
there's a lot of discussions what exactly is this בינתא Binta animal?
And I think תוספות Tosafot under בינתא Binta it says inside, פשיטא
דשרץ גמור הוא, Pshita desheretz gamur hu, right? ופירש בינתא כמו דג
קטן הנמצא במחרשה דקמשמע לן דנמצא במים היה מותר לפי שיש לו
קשקשים.
Ufeireish binta kemo dag katan hanimtza bamachreshah dekamashma lan denimtza bamayim
hayah mutar lefi sheyesh lo kaskasim. But here he's not נמצא במים.
Nimtza bamayim.
Okay. So this is a fish,
maybe. This is a fish that if we found it in the
water, if you pulled it out of the water, it would be
fine. But we didn't pull him out of the water, we pulled
him out of the dirt or out of... To be really kosher
fish, but
you just depends where you find it. Yes,
but we find it
because I assume if we found it where the plow is hitting
or like inside cabbage, it would be dead or dying or
something,
it would not be fit for eating.
A fish is but it doesn't mean you get מלקות malkot for
eating it. If I if there's like if you left a rancid
piece of salmon out there, right, and I ate it, I mean
it's not fit for eating but I wouldn't get מלקות malkot on
it.
Okay, I'm going to have to think about it, but it's almost
I my pushback wants to be it's almost like a נבלה nevelah
of a fish, no? Like
which a salmon is not, a salmon is already it was a
kosher fish, we fished it kosherly, we prepared it kosherly and now
it's spoiled. But this was a live thing and now for some
reason this live thing is wiggling inside a cabbage. This is תוספות'ס
Tosafot's idea, there's a lot of discussion about it, I'm not sure
if
the eel has to die out of the water. If you pull
the dead fish out of the water,
you
don't need to שחט shecht it.
It's not any more out of the water, it's somewhere else. No,
but I'm saying if would נבלה nevelah be like a dead fish
out of the water?
But you can do that.
I think you can eat that.
Why not? Because נבלה nevelah only applies to like you
know four-legged animals. Okay. So we this is this is as much
as תוספות Tosafot can help us and that if we don't like
it then we'll have to read other things about it. Okay.
And maybe some people don't think about it at all. Okay. מלקין
ליה. malkin leh.
Okay. מלקין ליה malkin leh משום שרץ השורץ על הארץ, mishum sheretz
hashortetz al ha'aretz, right? We have a פסוק pasuk that says כל
שרץ השורץ על הארץ שקץ הוא לא יאכל kol sheretz hashortetz al
ha'aretz sheketz hu lo ye'achel in ויקרא Vayikra 11 and where we
have all the laws of
כשרות. kashrut. Creepy-crawly disgusting things that are on the ground, then you're
going to get lashes. Don't eat it. Okay. ההוא דאכל בינתא
דבי כרבא, hahu de'achal binta devei karava, this little creature, ונגדיה רב
יהודה. venagdei Rav Yehuda. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda I guess doesn't agree,
so you can be with רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, that's fine.
Okay. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, another example, אכל פותיתא לוקה ארבעה. achal
putita lokei arba'ah. So now we have how many lashes do we
have for eating the different things? The understanding is that eating these
things, whatever they are, שרץ המים sheretz hamayim says רש''י Rashi about
the פותיתא, putita,
you swallow them whole because as we'll see in a second, if
you eat tiny bits, then you have to figure out if you
eat כזית kezayit before you have to be לוקה. lokei. So this
is a situation where for some reason you decided to swallow it
whole. Okay. אכל פותיתא לוקה ארבעה. achal putita lokei arba'ah. נמלה, nemalah,
we translate it as in modern Hebrew ant, so hopefully. לוקה חמש
lokei chamesh משום שרץ השורץ על הארץ. mishum sheretz hashortetz al ha'aretz.
So now it's not שרץ. sheretz.
I'm not sure why they add another מלקות. malkot. צרעה, tzirah,
wasp, לוקה שש lokei shesh משום שרץ העוף. mishum sheretz ha'of. So
we have an extra מלקות, malkot, extra lash because of
the flying creepy thing. אמר רב אחאי המשהה את נקביו עובר משום
לא תשקצו. amar Rav Achai hamash'he et nekavav over mishum lo teshaktzu.
Anybody has a clean translation for המשהה את נקביו? hamash'he et nekavav?
Somebody who doesn't go to the bathroom, somebody who does things that
are unclean also transgresses this commandment to be לא תשקצו. lo teshaktzu.
Do you get מלקות? malkot?
I guess. Not go to the bathroom
long enough.
When he's getting מלקות malkot he's going to end
up going to the bathroom, right? Okay.
Alright. Next disgusting thing. אמר רב ביבי בר אביי האי מן דשתי
בקרנא דאומנא קעבר משום דלא תשקצו.
amar Rav Bibi bar Abaye hai man deshti bekarna
de'umna ka'avar mishum delo teshaktzu. What about somebody who's drinking from a
vessel of somebody who's a bloodletter? Also that is considered something disgusting
and he also transgresses לא תשקצו. lo teshaktzu. אמר רבא בר רב
הונא, amar Rava bar Rav Huna,
he's one of my heroes, I'm not sure why he brings this
here. Okay. ריסק תשע נמלים והביא אחד חי והשלימן לכזית לוקה. rissek
tesha nemalim vehevi echad chai vehishliman lekezayit lokei. Okay. You take nine
ants and you smash them and then you bring one living one
and you have a כזית, kezayit, then you get לוקה ו'. lokei
vav. Sorry, you get six מלקות. malkot. חמש משום בריה ואחד משום
כזית. chamesh mishum biryah ve'echad mishum kezayit. Five מלקות malkot because you
have like a full animal there
and one מלקות malkot because you ate כזית. kezayit. נבלה רבה אמר
רבי יוחנן אפילו. nevela Rabba amar Rabbi Yochanan afilu. נבלה רבה אמר
רבי יוחנן אפילו שנים והוא. Neveilah rabbah amar Rabi Yochanan afilu shenayim
vehu. רבי יוסף אמר אפילו אחד והוא. Rabi Yosef amar afilu echad
vehu. ולא פליגי הא ברבתא והא בזוטרתא. Velo pligi ha brabbasa veha
bzutarsa. Okay, so now we have a great argument, how many מלקות
malkos for how many smashed שרצים shratzim do you get? And if
it matters, okay,
is it two plus one? Two smashed, one plus one for one?
One smashed plus one? And they says לא פליגי, lo pligi,
isn't that comforting? There is no debate. Here we're talking about big
ants and here we're talking about little ants. Short thing is, don't
eat disgusting things.
Somebody would have to be warned about all this, right? Somebody's sitting
there and saying you have six, you have...
Right, right, you're now going to the solo.
I can do just a little bit more and then we'll pause.
אכל טבל ומעשר ראשון Achal tevel u'maaser rishon etcetera. This is among
the people that get lashed, people that eat
from the טבל ומעשר ראשון. tevel u'maaser rishon. אמר רב אכל טבל
של מעשר עני לוקה. Amar Rav achal tevel shel maaser ani lokeh.
כמאן דהאי תנא דתניא. Keman d'hai tanna detanya. Okay.
If a person eats from what we were supposed to give to
the poor person,
he can be לוקה. lokeh. אמר רבי יוסי יכול לא יהא חייב
אלא על הטבל שלא הורם ממנו כל עיקר. Amar Rabi Yosei yachol
lo yehei chayav ela al hatevel shelo huram mimenu kol ikkar. הורם
ממנו תרומה גדולה ולא הורם ממנו מעשר ראשון. Huram mimenu terumah gedolah
velo huram mimenu maaser rishon. מעשר ראשון ולא מעשר שני ואפילו מעשר
עני מנין? Maaser rishon velo maaser sheni va'afilu maaser ani minayin? תלמוד
לומר לא תוכל לאכל בשעריך. Talmud lomar lo suchal le'echol bish'arecha.
And then says, you can't eat in your gate, ולהלן הוא אומר
ואכלו בשעריך ושבעו. v'lehallan hu omer v'achlu bish'arecha v'save'u. מה להלן מעשר
עני, Mah lehallan maaser ani, מעשר עני, maaser ani, sorry, אף כאן
מעשר עני. af kan maaser ani. ואמר רחמנא לא תוכל. Ve'amar Rachmana
lo suchal. So this is another example, which maybe starts from that
tomorrow morning of
a negative that is followed by a positive and how do we
deal with both? You can't eat until you were מפריש, mafrish, until
you gave a section away for the poor person,
and that will determine your מלקות malkos for this last case of
אכל טבל ומעשר ראשון. achal tevel u'maaser rishon. With that, thank you
so much for being with us this morning and a wonderful day.
Thank
you.